Guide to the George Bernard Shaw letters and documents, 1900-1972.
Shaw, George Bernard letters and documents
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
George Bernard Shaw letters and documents, 1900-1972.
8495
Shaw, Bernard,
0.5 cubic feet.
Manuscripts
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Letters and documents relating to George Bernard Shaw; also, a sample of his hair.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Letters and documents relating to George Bernard Shaw; also, a sample of his hair.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950.; Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Stock "Letter of Thanks" response to letters about Shaw's controversial 1914 Essay, "Common Sense About the War". Includes unsigned photograph of Shaw, Rudin # Sh-1; Format: ANS; Location: 10 Adelphi Terrace, WC (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Recipient: George A. Greenwood
  - Political activist Shaw calls the recipient's attention to "Properly qualified men for the official staff", October 31, 1900; Rudin # Sh-2; Format: TLS; Location: London, England (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Recipient: Dear Sir
  - Shaw replies to Cotterill with brief note written on post card photograph of Shaw, 1908; Rudin # Sh-3; Format: ANS; Location: London, England (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Recipient: Erica Cotterill
  - Shaw tells Cotterill to get married instead of going after married men, including him. Photo of Shaw and cameo portrait of Cotterill included, April 27, 1908; Rudin # Sh-4; Format: ALS; Location: 10 Adelphi Terrace, WC (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Shaw criticizes Cotterill's handwriting and firmly tells her what to do, July 9, 1909; Rudin # Sh-5; Format: ALS; Location: 10 Adelphi Terrace, WC (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Shaw offers Murray a chance to translate Cyrano de Bergerac, December 3, 1909; Rudin # Sh-6; Format: TLS; Location: 10 Adelphi Terrace, WC (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Recipient: Gilbert Murray, Esq.
  - Shaw responds to an invitation, "You already have twelve speakers, which is about eight more than human nature can bear", May 3, 1911; Rudin # Sh-7; Format: TLS; Location: 10 Adelphi Terrace, WC (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Recipient: William Poel
  - Shaw discusses the first NY production of his play, "Major Barbara", January 10, 1916; Rudin # Sh-8; Format: Postcard; Location: 10 Adelphi Terrace, WC (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Recipient: David H. Wallace
  - Shaw remarks on making a booklet, "Know Thyself", and unrelated printed card discussing Shaw's appeal for a British alphabet, January 9, 1917; Rudin # Sh-9; Format: Card, ALS; Location: 10 Adelphi Terrace, WC (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Recipient: Curtis Freshel
  - Shaw refuses to have his letters quoted as advertisements, protecting his literary reputation, March 20, 1917; Rudin # Sh-10; Format: ALS; Location: 10 Adelphi Terrace, WC (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Recipient: Phelan Gibb
  - Shaw's TMS "General Maurice's alleged breach of discipline" and letter from the Daily Chronicle declining publication, May 19, May 21, 1918; Rudin # Sh-10A; Format: TMS, TLS; Location: Ayot St. Lawrence, Welwyn, Herts (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Recipient: Editor of the Daily Chronicle, My Dear Shaw
  - Shaw gives his strong opinions concerning the proposed demolition of the Waterloo bridge. Accompanied by Baring's unsigned response, January 20, 1926; Rudin # Sh-12; Format: ALS; Location: Ayot St. Lawrence, Welwyn, Herts (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Recipient: Maurice Baring
  - Letter of thanks for a book on hanging with a discussion of printing corrections and reference to William Morris, November 17, 1928; Rudin # Sh-13; Format: TLS; Location: 4 Whitehall Court, London, SWI (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Recipient: H Daus, Esq.
  - Shaw declines offer to publish "The Apple Cart". Including a photo of Shaw from 1932, August 16, 1929; Rudin # Sh-14; Format: Personal postcard; Location: Ayot St. Lawrence, Welwyn, Herts (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Recipient: Isaac Don Levine, Book League of America
  - Shaw reminiscing about the first production of his play, "Arms and the Man", January 15, 1931; Rudin # Sh-16; Format: TLS; Location: Whitehall Court 130, London SWI (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Recipient: John Drinkwater
  - Shaw does not like the work of painter Austin Spare and declines to go to an exhibit to purchase his art, May 4,1932; Rudin # Sh-17; Format: TLS; Location: 4 Whitehall Court, London, SWI (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Recipient: GS Sandilands, Esq.
  - Shaw replies to McIntosh telling her there is not a part that will fit her in his new play, September 14, 1933; Rudin # Sh-18; Format: Autograph postcard; Location: Malverne (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Recipient: Madge McIntosh
  - Two applications for renewal of license for mechanically propelled road vehicles, with photo of Shaw, December 17, 1934; December 15, 1941; Rudin # Sh-20; Format: TDS; Location: Hertfordshire CC (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Shaw sets out his views on the post-war economic relationship the allies will face versus Germany, October 20, 1918; Rudin # Sh-23; Format: TLS; Location: 10 Adelphi Terrace, WC (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Recipient: Professor Halperine-Kaminsky
  - Response to an interview request on a printed card that declines requests to author a preface, March 14, 1928; Rudin # Sh-25; Format: Printed postcard; Location: 4 Whitehall Court, London, SWI (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Recipient: Ben Greet Jr.
  - Letter regarding the influence of World War I on classical music, April 11, 1918; Rudin # Sh-26; Format: TLS; Location: 10 Adelphi Terrace, WG (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Shaw writes about Glare Boothe Lucy's performance in "Candida", June 21, 1946; Rudin # Sh-27; Format: TLS; Location: Whitehall Court, London SWI (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Recipient: My dear Emarel, Mrs. Curtis Freshel
  - Quoting Woodrow Wilson, Shaw responds, March 22, 1928; Rudin # Sh-28; Format: TLS; Location: Whitehall Court, London, SWI (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Recipient: Dear Sir, JT Jones
  - Shaw says "You surely don't want to vote for Judas Iscariot", October 20, 1931; Rudin # Sh-24; Format: ALS; Location: Ayot St. Lawrence, Welwyn, Herts (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Shaw tries to persuade Actress violet Vanbrugh to play his heroine in "Man and Superman". She did not accept. Accompanied by copy of his book, catalogued separately, December 28, 1900; Rudin # Sh-29; Format: ALS; Location: Maybury Knoll Woking (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Recipient: Dear Mrs. Bourchier (Violet Vanbrugh)
  - Shaw responds to a request for a lock of his hair, July 24, 1944; Rudin # Sh-22; Format: Postcard; Location: Hertfordshire (Mapcase-item 1)
    Recipient: FE Loewenstein
- (Series II. Manuscripts and Documents)
  - Auction catalogue, with GB Shaw materials, May 9, 1972; Rudin # Sh-19; Location: Sotheby Park-Bernet Public Auction, New York (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Shaw's own carbon copy of a prologue to BBC performance of his play, April 22, 1938; Rudin # Sh-21; Format: Typed manuscript (Box 1, Folder 26)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Bound Items
Saint Joan: a Chronicle Play in Six Scenes and an Epilogue, with 7 pages of autographs of actors. Also includes letters and cards. Rudin # SH-11
Man and Superman, George Bernard Shaw. Rudin # SH- 29